Bryan Forst

bryanforst@gmail.com skype: bryanforst linkedin.com/in/bforst

A Senior Software Developer who has created business applications in the Finance, Health, Education and Human Resource fields. I've worked on technical and business application projects for clients from small startups to large corporate environments. My expertise is developing flexible systems with user and business centered designs.

I am a developer who enjoys consulting in many different domains. My interest is understanding a problem that needs solving, proposing and then building solutions. Despite our greatly expanded technological skills, analysis is still the key to implementing a successful solution. Back in the day 2 and 3 tier systems were a huge challenge, now N-tiers are almost automatically deployed.

Been through the rigors of waterfall into the lighter weight world of iterative, XP and now Agile development. Change is inevitable, so we need to be as light as is reasonably possible while maintaining accuracy and reliability.

My current tool set is my current tool set. Over 30 years it has changed drastically and will change again. Languages are meant to be used where their strengths match the product and business needs. I strive for good analysis and flexibility.

I've developed systems before and after the use of test-driven development and believe all environments benefit from as much TDD as they can handle. This means automated builds, daily deliveries, test suites. Without these refactoring is only done when it cannot be avoided and quality suffers. TDD is an essential best practice.

I learn tools as needed and have extensive experience with older technologies that informs my choice of current tools. Giant furballs of legacy code do not scare me and greenfield environments are like beautiful vistas of endless potential.

Languages/Tools: ant, Ajax, C, C#, Subversion, Git, Hibernate, Java, Javascript, jQuery,

JSP, jUnit, .Net, Struts/Tiles, Resin, PHP, Tomcat, SQL, NoSQL,

Smalltalk, Spring – Other ancient technologies

Professional Experience

Thinking Industries: Seattle, WA 2011 – present

b3tz.com

Remote Consultant

Developing social media game consisting of bet publishing modules and consumer play, rewards and tracking. Intially built inside Facebook framework and as embedded tile in blog posts. Have since moved out of the FB world using Shiro tools to enable FB and other login credentials. Technical Environment: java, jsp, jquery, Shiro, mongoDB, tomcat, jUnit, ant, svn, FB API, AWS/Ubuntu

Bryan Forst Page 2

Uran Software Services: Kolkata, India

http://www.uransoftware.com/

Technical Advisor

Providing training and management expertise for a BPO startup. Client services include software testing, web content updating, website creation and maintenance, internet information research and document processing. Uran is a socially responsible business hiring graduates from Uddami Computer Training Centre.

Technical Environment: Challenging

Advisory Group: Chicago, IL

2014 - 2015

2007 - Present

Remote Consultant

Analyzed and optimized large SQL queries for a healthcare financial system.

Technical Environment: Java, Oracle SQL, ant, git

OptiLink: Portland, OR

2006 - 2011

Remote Consultant

Developed automatic build process for database and scripting procedures. Worked with team on implementing test driven development using mock objects, refactoring and automated agile processes. Creating outsource testing group for the main software product.

Maintenance and enhancements to product based on customer demands.

Technical Environment: .Net, C#, nUnit, nAnt, DBGhost

Intell-Assess: Orinda, CA

2007 - 2008

Remote Consultant

Developing web-based curriculum building software that coordinates lessons by State and Federal standards. Responsible for development in all areas, unit testing, etc. in distributed agile model.

Technical Environment: Java, Hibernate, WebWorks, Ant. MySQL

<u>Uddami Computer Training Centre:</u> Calcutta, India

1998 – Present

http://www.uddamiindiafoundation.org

Technical Advisor

Providing technical assistance for non-profit conducting technology training in India. Responsible for hardware and software evaluation, purchase, installation, troubleshooting and training. Created curriculum and teaching classes from beginning computers to specialized vocational subjects such as business office, internet, graphics.

Technical Environment: Challenging

Classroom Connect: San Francisco, CA

2002 - 2005

Consultant

Assisted programming teams learning test-driven-development using jUnit and ant. Developed automatic build process for creation and testing of integration environment for programming teams. Implemented semi-automatic processes for updating testing and production environments. Developed web based professional development applications for teachers. Technical Environment: Java, Javascript, Struts and Tiles, Ant, Hibernate, Spring, Resin

Philosopher's Stone: Los Angeles, California

2001

Consultant

Assumed project management and mentoring duties while steering a pre-Beta project back on track. Did design and prototype implementation on a distributed monitoring system.

Technical Environment: VisualAge Smalltalk (VAST), Java

Artintel Systems: Calcutta, India

2000 - 2001

http://www.artintelsystems.com

Vice President, Software Technology

Defined strategy, infrastructure, training and development processes for a staff of 12 software developers. Met with potential clients. Managed projects for international clients. Responsible for designing software and mentoring staff on agile (it was called XP back then) development process.

Bharat Books and Art: Calcutta, India

1999 - 2001

http://www.bharatbooks.com

Co-Founder

Created web site selling Bengali books and art. Responsible for all aspects of site hosting and creation, web promotion, order handling.

Technical Environment: HTML, CGI, Javascript

Evolve Software Incorporated: San Francisco, CA

1997 - 1998

Senior Software Developer

Designed and developed abstract metadata components of a generic application development framework for this startup company. Developed Enterprise Service Automation application allowing Evolve to define and enter a new market of Enterprise Software.

Technical Environment: Win 95/NT, Forte, VisualCafe(Java)

TesserAct Technology: San Francisco, CA

1996

Senior Design Engineer

Designed key components for a highly adaptive, distributed HR product. Led an integrated team of analysts, QA, and development staff. Responsible for mentoring staff on Smalltalk techniques along with development duties.

Technical Environment: Win 95/NT, Smalltalk VSE, XP development process.

CG Computer Services: San Francisco, CA

1990 - 1996

Senior Analyst/Consultant

Provided application design and development expertise to a variety of medium to large Bay Area companies. Worked on increasingly complex object-oriented development projects. Specialized in PC and client-server projects.

Paradigm Corporation

1995 - 1996

Designed distributed architecture for next generation replacement for current production system. Also developed workflow enhancements for existing system.

Technical Environment: Win3.1, SQLWindow, SQLServer

Systems Programming Limited

1995 - 1996

Installed customer requested modification to product developed as Lead Engineer in 1994.

Technical Environment: Win3.1, Team/V, Oracle v7, ODBC

TesserAct Corporation

1995

Installed customer requested enhancements to product released in 1993. Handled all details of project; customer contact, estimating, programming, and delivery of enhancements for acceptance testing.

Technical Environment: OS/2, Smalltalk/V, MSC

Integrated Software Solutions Incorporated

1994 - 1995

Delivered two successful production releases of a railway monitoring system. Gathered requirements and analyzed proposals for major future product release. Provided analysis of current development and testing practices and proposed new methodologies for improvement.

Technical Environment: OS/2, Mozart

Systems Programming Limited

1994 - 1995

Lead Software Engineer developing a system to track and report on Medicare and Medical applicants for the State Department of Health Services. Responsible for introduction of object-oriented theory and practices to team members.

Technical Environment: Win 3.1, Smalltalk Team/V, Oracle v6, ODBC

Walker Interactive

1993 - 1994

Member of senior design team that analyzed and designed a new Client/Server architecture for mainframe financial applications and customization tools.

Tesseract Corporation

1992 - 1993

Developed a strategic Human Resources product designed to provide a distributed processing architecture. Process included heavy collaboration with end users and consultants.

Technical Environment: OS/2, Win3.1, Smalltalk/V

<u>Chevron USA</u> 1991 – 1992

Assisted Chevron team in developing several HR application providing client front ends to mainframe database systems. Responsible for mentoring staff members and investigating new technologies for innovative application use.

Technical Environment: OS/2, Smalltalk/V

VISA Corporation

1990 - 1991

Created specifications and prototype projects for Finance department. Maintained and enhanced production systems. Worked closely with financial managers to create new profitable systems.

Technical Environment: Dos/Win3.0, dBase, Oracle, Smalltalk/V

Bryan Forst Consulting: Oakland, CA

1989 - 1990

Principal

Developed an aircraft maintenance tracking system for a major domestic airline. System handled a high volume of reporting and transaction requests interactively from mechanics Technical Environment: Vax/VMS, RDMS, DEC-C

Bryan Forst Consulting: Madison, WI

1986 - 1989

Principal

Provided contract analysis and programming to Wisconsin businesses. Converted mainframe systems into PC database applications to reduce costs and improve productivity. Developed new applications for medical, library information, and engineering industries. Provided programming, training, and consulting for owners of PC systems and businesses.

Technical Environment: DOS/Windows, xBase, MS-C, Assembler, APL, Fortran

Professional Associations/Other Accomplishments	
Co-Founder, North Bay Smalltalk Users Group	1990
Member, California Alumni Association	1989 - Present
Member, Association for Computing Machinery	1994 – 1998
Volunteer, CompuMentor	1989 – 1995
CG Computer Services Significant Contributor Award	1994
CG Computer Services Major Contributor Award	1995

Education

B.A. Mathematics, University of California - Berkeley, CA 1981